Let's look at AVEC in action.
Meet Svea and her colleague Bo.
They've worked together for almost five years,
but at times they struggle to maintain
a positive and productive relationship at work.
Bo sometimes has difficulty listening to Svea.
He has a habit of letting his mind wander,
and when he suddenly thinks of a great idea, he tends to blurt it out,
unintentionally interrupting her.
At times Bo's behavior irritates Svea.
She wonders if he only cares about his own ideas and opinions,
since he often fails to listen to hers.
Once in a meeting he interrupted her,
then suggested a new idea she had shared with him only the day before.
Bo was totally unaware he had done it.
Svea finds that she's often not very excited to work with Bo
and prefers to work with others.
For her part, Svea can be quick to judgment.
While she rarely says anything explicitly to Bo,
her annoyance shows.
Bo suspects her cross looks are often directed at him,
though he's never asked her about it.
But Bo thinks Svea is judging his ideas or his style, or both.
Or perhaps she simply doesn't like him.
The reality is that most of the time,
she's merely annoyed that he doesn't seem to listen.
Bo has started disengaging during these interactions,
and Svea finds herself jumping in and interrupting Bo
when he does speak.
Over time their strained relationship has started
to affect their productivity and effectiveness.
What if each of them could approach this with more attention,
vulnerability, empathy and compassion?
Imagine Bo actively listening to Svea's point of view
and asking more questions.
And what if, instead of keeping her emotions to herself,
Svea shared her feelings directly and openly?
What if that, in turn, helped each of them to put themselves in each other's shoes
and to genuinely commit to helping one another?
AVEC helps us build interpersonal resilience,
and it makes the difference between a relationship being the thing that helps you overcome challenges
versus the relationship actually being the challenge.